Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today's daf דף daf is
Yud Aleph י"א. Yud Aleph. Thanks to Yosef for covering and we
pick up about what is it 18-19 down or so and we're
in the middle of these Psichas פתיחתא. Psichas. Rava pasach רבא פתח.
Rava pasach. The line starts with the word
Hashem shehayah lanu bekumeinu adam, adam velo melech ה' שהיה לנו בקומנו
אדם, אדם ולא מלך. Hashem shehayah lanu bekumeinu adam, adam velo melech.
Rava pasach רבא פתח. Rava pasach. Now if anybody has learned Midrash
Rabbah מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah you know, yeah you know that Midrash
Rabbah מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah starts often with a Psicha פתיחה, Psicha,
like often starts this way. It quotes a pasuk פסוק pasuk from
elsewhere. Now Midrash Rabbah מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah is going on pesukim
פסוקים pesukim in the Torah תורה, Torah, so it often quotes a
pasuk פסוק pasuk from Nach נ"ך, Nach, often a pasuk פסוק pasuk
that you've never heard before and manages to find a way to
like weave in an obscure pasuk פסוק pasuk and say that this
really relates to the story, you know find a way to sort
of connect it to the story in the Torah תורה. Torah. So
here you're dealing with a similar type of a mode, a Psicha
פתיחה, Psicha, but this is like Midrashim מדרשים Midrashim in Megillat Esther
מגילת אסתר Megillat Esther as we see, you know what the Gemara
גמרא Gemara has been doing is it basically starts from the beginning
of the Megillah מגילה Megillah by Vayehi bimei Achashverosh ויהי בימי אחשורוש
Vayehi bimei Achashverosh and it just goes of like pesukim פסוקים pesukim
by pesukim פסוקים pesukim essentially what the Gemara גמרא Gemara is doing,
you know and it's a very strange phenomenon. It's like with no
preamble, it's basically giving us like the Midrash Rabbah מדרש רבה Midrash
Rabbah on Esther אסתר, Esther, pesukim פסוקים pesukim by pesukim פסוקים pesukim
and giving us like Amoraic Midrashim מדרשים Midrashim around it, and it's
actually relating to the fact that there would be this you know
mode of Psicha פתיחה, Psicha, that when you open learning Esther אסתר
Esther you quote some pasuk פסוק pasuk from somewhere else and then
you find a way you know to tie it in. So this
was like the classic mode of beginning with a Midrashim מדרשים Midrashim
on a sefer ספר. sefer. So number one it's important to just
be aware of that, you know I think that's sort of like
the genre that we're dealing with. Of course the other point that
I'll make which I've been saying a lot is that, and again
I don't claim that this is as I just said distinctive for
Megilla מגילה, Megilla, this is very standard but what you achieve by
a Psicha פתיחה Psicha is you sort of create this sense of
you know of the unification of all of the biblical texts of
all of Tanakh תנ"ך. Tanakh. So certainly it works like if a
later pasuk פסוק pasuk in the Nevi'im נביאים Nevi'im is referring back
to this like you know story in the Torah תורה, Torah, like
it's all interconnected. Now it's one thing of course to be starting
with the Torah תורה Torah and doing a pasuk פסוק pasuk from
Nach נ"ך, Nach, you know okay it's interconnected but the other text
came later so it's not such a chidush חידוש chidush you know
whatever to say later pesukim פסוקים pesukim are alluding back like you
know to this story. But nevertheless it communicates a sense that it's
all sort of it's all one big interconnected text. But again there's
a particular power as I've been saying by starting from pesukim פסוקים
pesukim in Esther אסתר Esther which is at the very end of
Tanakh תנ"ך Tanakh and relating it back to earlier pesukim פסוקים pesukim
especially since so many of the Psichas פתיחתא Psichas are biblical pesukim
פסוקים, pesukim, you know again to create that sense of it being
an integral part of Tanakh תנ"ך Tanakh even this very late book
is already foreshadowed, the ideas of it already being earlier told in
these earlier pesukim פסוקים pesukim in the Torah תורה, Torah, so that
certainly one of the things that gets communicated through this mode of
this Psicha פתיחה. Psicha. So let's take a look where we pick
up with Rava רבא. Rava. Rava pasach רבא פתח Rava pasach lapitcha
l'ha parshata לפתחא להא פרשתא. lapitcha l'ha parshata. Rava רבא Rava opened
up the pitcha פתחא, pitcha, the beginning of this parsha פרשה parsha
of Megilla מגילה Megilla meihacha מהכא meihacha from the following verse. Birbot
tzadikim yismach ha'am ברבות צדיקים ישמח העם Birbot tzadikim yismach ha'am with
the increase of the righteous
the nation will rejoice, uvimshol rasha ye'aneich am ובמשול רשע יאנח עם
uvimshol rasha ye'aneich am and with the dominion of the wicked the
people will moan. Birbot tzadikim yismach ha'am ברבות צדיקים ישמח העם Birbot
tzadikim yismach ha'am zeh Mordechai ve'Esther זה מרדכי ואסתר zeh Mordechai ve'Esther
d'ketiv vayeshu Shushan tzahala vesameicha דכתיב והעיר שושן צהלה ושמחה. d'ketiv v'ha'ir
Shushan tzahala v'sameicha. When things were good for them the entire city
of Shushan שושן Shushan was joyous and rejoicing. Uvimshol rasha ye'aneich am
ובמשול רשע יאנח עם uvimshol rasha ye'aneich am and when the wicked
is you know has dominion the people will moan, zeh Haman זה
המן zeh Haman d'ketiv veha'ir Shushan navocha דכתיב והעיר שושן נבוכה. d'ketiv
veha'ir Shushan navocha. And the city of Shushan שושן Shushan was bewildered,
was distraught. Rav Masna amar meiha רב מתנה אמר מהכא. Rav Masna
amar meiha. Rav Masna רב מתנה Rav Masna would open from the
following pasuk פסוק: pasuk: Ki mi goy gadol asher lo elohim kerovim
eilav k'hashem elokeinu bechol koreinu eilav כי מי גוי גדול אשר לו
אלקים קרובים אליו כה' אלקינו בכל קראנו אליו Ki mi goy gadol
asher lo elohim kerovim eilav k'Hashem elokeinu bechol koreinu eilav which is
an interesting pasuk פסוק pasuk you know because that pasuk פסוק pasuk
sort of reflects an idea like of the sense of confidence, God
is always with us whenever we call out to him. Of course
you know the story of Purim פורים Purim was this sense that
God was not close, that God's name isn't even there and you
know there's this sense of imminent danger. And it's only at the
very last minute that things get reversed, but okay when you look
at it in hindsight you can say bechol koreinu eilav בכל קראנו
אליו, bechol koreinu eilav, at the time maybe that wasn't necessarily the
feeling. But at the end even the story of Purim פורים Purim
is look even in a time when God feels absent we called
out to God and God was there for us. Rav Ashi amar
meiha רב אשי אמר מהכא. Rav Ashi amar meiha. Or hanissah elohim
lavo lakachat lo goy mikerev goy bemasos uv'otot uv'moftim uv'milchama או הנסה
אלקים לבוא לקחת לו גוי מקרב גוי במסת באתת ובמופתים ובמלחמה, Or
hanissah elohim lavo lakachat lo goy mikerev goy bemasos uv'otot uv'moftim uv'milchama,
you know kechol asher asah Hashem elokeichem lachem bemitzrayim l'einecha ככל אשר
עשה ה' אלקיכם לכם במצרים לעיניך. kechol asher asah Hashem elokeichem lachem
bemitzrayim l'einecha. Like God ever done this tremendous thing. Again quite fascinating
taking a verse from Yetziat Mitzrayim יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim where it's
about nes galui נס גלוי nes galui and God's presence is so
evident to all and showing you know here too you know ultimately
even though here it was a period of like hester panim הסתר
פנים hester panim in the end this is also what happened you
know the same type of a thing so even in a time
when it seemed like it wasn't going to happen it happened. One
also wonders if there's a hint to the idea of lavo lakachat
lo goy mikerev goy לבוא לקחת לו גוי מקרב גוי lavo lakachat
lo goy mikerev goy because the whole message of Purim פורים Purim
was the degree of assimilation you know and the people were like
you know they were like you know they were like. It was,
you know, there's מדרשים Midrashim about how the people totally have been
lost. It was only because of אחשורוש Achashverosh and the fact that
he was oppressing them, which ultimately led to them to crystallize, you
know, their like identity, otherwise they would have completely assimilated. So, you
know, so there's that sense of לבוא לקחת לו גוי מקרב גוי
Lavo Lakahas Lo Goy Mikerev Goy that they're
re-sort-of-separated out, you know, and get once again their distinctiveness in that
process of the מגילה. Megillah. Did you want to say something though?
Okay. So, ויהי
בימי אחשורוש, Vayehi Bimei Achashverosh, so that is the end of the
פתיחה. Psicha. So now and now,
so now that we end with like how you would introduce it,
the פסוקים Psukim you would sort of tie it into from elsewhere
in תנ"ך, Tanakh, now we're going to, it's really a מדרש רבה
Midrash Rabbah is what we have here, now we're going to get
to a פסוק Pasuk by פסוק Pasuk analysis of the מגילה. Megillah.
And it was in the time of אחשורוש. Achashverosh. So אמר רב,
Amar Rav, וי והי. Vay Vehi. So ויהי, Vayehi, וי Vay is
woe and moaning בימי אחשורוש Bimei Achashverosh in the time of אחשורוש.
Achashverosh. הדא דכתיב Hada Dechisiv
and this is what's meant by the verse or this is the
fulfillment of the verse, והתמכרתם
שם לאויביך לעבדים ולשפחות ואין קונה, Vehismakartem Sham Le'oyvecha La'avadim Velishfachos V'ein
Koneh, you'll be sold to your enemies and nobody will want to
purchase you. Now, where does רב Rav see the fulfillment of that
verse? I mean clearly there's woe and moaning, right, so hold on.
So clearly there's, you know, the edict against them but why specifically
that verse? So רש"י Rashi says,
where's
רש"י? Rashi? מה שכתוב בתורה ואין קונה גזר המן שלא יהיה אדם
משעבד מהם לעבד. Ma Shekasuv BaTorah V'ein Koneh Gazar Haman Shelo Yihiyeh
Adam Meshabed Mehem Le'eved. People said you can't buy a Jewish slave.
So, you know, now I don't know why that's a bad thing
or whatever maybe but they, you know, but they had no money
and they were starving to death and they needed to sell themselves
and nobody would buy. But I actually thought that it was referring
to a different point. I actually thought that it was the fact
that המן Haman wanted, well but, Michael says correctly, you know, אסתר
Esther says, what'd she say? ואלו לעבדים ולשפחות נמכרנו החרשתי. V'ilu La'avadim
Velishfachos Nimkarnu Hecherashti. Had we been sold, so had we been sold,
but we hadn't been sold. Why not? Because ואין קונה Ve'ein Koneh
maybe, but it certainly evokes that ואלו לעבדים ולשפחות נמכרנו V'ilu La'avadim
Velishfachos Nimkarnu and והתמכרתם שם לאויביך לעבדים ולשפחות. Vehismakartem Sham Le'oyvecha La'avadim
Velishfachos. I also thought that it was alluding to the verse of
what do you call it, of that המן Haman wants to give
the money and אחשורוש Achashverosh says, הכסף נתון לך. Hakesef Nasun Lach.
I don't want to take the money. So here it is, they
want to, he wants to buy them not לעבדים ולשפחות, La'avadim Velishfachos,
but to kill them and he refuses to even take the money.
So anyway, certainly there are some echoes of this in
the
מגילה. Megillah. ושמואל אמר, U'Shmuel Amar, לא מאסתים ולא געלתים לכלותם. Lo
Me'astim Velo Ge'altim Lechalosam. לא מאסתים בימי יונים, Lo Me'astim Bimei Yevanim,
I did not despise them at the time of the Greeks, at
the time of the story of חנוכה. Chanukah. It looked like they
were being abandoned but in the end, you know, in the end
there was the victory. ולא געלתים בימי נבוכדנצר, Velo Ge'altim Bimei Nevuchadnezzar,
in the time of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar it looked like the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash was destroyed but in the end they were not forgotten.
לכלותם Lechalosam
to destroy them בימי המן. Bimei Haman. It looked like they would
be completely wiped out in the time of המן Haman but that
didn't happen either. להפר בריתי אתם בימי פרסיים, Lehafer Brisi Itam Bimei
Parsiyim,
to abandon my covenant with them in the time of the Persians,
not exactly clear exactly what specific event that that is referring to.
כי אני השם אלוהיהם, Ki Ani Hashem Elokeihem, I am השם Hashem
their God בימי גוג ומגוג. Bimei Gog U'Magog.
So until then I haven't abandoned them. I won't let them be
totally destroyed, wiped out, the religion destroyed, but ultimately the revelation of
כי אני השם אלוהיכם Ki Ani Hashem Elokeichem that, you know, sort
of seeing the full expression of being their God, that will come
in the messianic period of time of גוג ומגוג. Gog U'Magog. Yes.
אבני נזר Avnei Nezer says that the reference in
נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar is actually a censoring that's originally רומיים.
Romiyim. It's actually what originally? אספסיינוס. Aspasyanos. אספסיינוס? Aspasyanos? Oh. בימי פרסיים
Bimei Parsiyim is אספסיינוס? Aspasyanos? Interesting. That's interesting.
He said it was
changed.
Right, right, right. It's interesting because we're going to see פרסיים Parsiyim
later which clearly it also refers to a Roman. נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnezzar. Oh,
נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar was originally אספסיינוס. Aspasyanos. That's interesting.
That's interesting.
He said it was just to avoid offending the Romans.
Did he say what בימי פרסיים Bimei Parsiyim is though?
He said it's Persians. Persian.
Yeah, but is there anything specifically about what in the Persian period?
No. Okay. Because later we're going to see a Persian which I
think actually means Roman and I was wondering about the גירסא, Girsa,
so you'll tell me about it when we get to it. Okay.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. תנא ברייתא, Tana Braisa, לא מאסתים בימי כשדים
Lo Me'astim Bimei Kasdim in the time of the
כשדים, Kasdim, שהעמדתי להם דניאל חנניה מישאל ועזריה. She'emadeti Lahem Daniel Chananyah
Mishael V'Azaryah. So here's where God has come, you know, to sort
of save us through the leaders that came at that time. So
דניאל חנניה מישאל ועזריה, Daniel Chananyah Mishael V'Azaryah, they came and they...
not, you know, they sort of stood up for God and for
the religion and they did not, you know, חנניה מישאל ועזריה Chananyah
Mishael v'Azaryah let themselves be thrust into the
fire. ולא געלתים v'lo ge'altim בימי יוונים bi'ymei Yevanim in the time
of the Greeks, where the Seleucid Greeks, where שמעון הצדיק, Shimon HaTzaddik,
the sort of leader of the time, וחשמונאי ובניו ומתתיהו כהן גדול,
v'Chashmonai u'vanav u'Mattisyahu Kohen Gadol, right? And the Chashmonayim and and and
those religious leaders. ולא כלותם v'lo chalotam בימי המן, bi'ymei Haman, I
did not let them be destroyed in the time of Haman, שהעמדתי
להם מרדכי ואסתר, she'he'emadti lahem Mordechai v'Esther, okay, clearly. להפר בריתי אתם
l'hafer briti itam to abandon my covenant with them בימי פרסיים bi'ymei
Parsiyim in the time of the Persians, שהעמדתי להם של בית רבי
וחכמי דורות she'he'emadti lahem shel Beis Rebbe v'chachmei dorot that I made
come, rise up for them the house of Rebbe and the sages
of the generations. Now the problem is that that is not the
time of the Persians, so here's where clearly I think the original
גרסא girsa must be the Romans. That is exactly, so that's where
Steinzaltz said, yeah, thank you. Okay, so the ברייתא, B'raisa, מותני מתניתיהם.
motni matnis'hom. Yeah, correct, apparently this is a ברייתא. B'raisa. So וחשמונאי
ובניו ומתתיהו כהן גדול, v'Chashmonai u'vanav u'Mattisyahu Kohen Gadol, so who's the
Chashmonai? It's not what I guess, all of the Chashmonayim, I mean,
Mattisyahu and his sons. Yeah, it's true, וחשמונאי ובניו, v'Chashmonai u'vanav, yeah,
it's a good question, I don't know why it's phrased that way.
Okay, כי אני השם אלוהיהם ki Ani Hashem Elokeihem לעתיד לבוא l'asid
l'avo in the future, שאין כל אומה ולשון יכולים לשלוט בהם, she'ein
kol umah v'lashon yecholim lishlot bahem, in the end they will be,
not only will I not prevent them from being destroyed, but also
I, you know, they will be truly seen as my nation that
nobody else will ever have dominion over them, they won't be subjugated
under other nations. Okay, so beginning the story of Purim, this is
a little bit, no longer, it sounds to me it's a little
doubling back. We're no longer on the ויהי בימי אחשורוש V'yehi Bi'ymei
Achashveirosh דרשנין, darshanin, the opening פסוקים. pesukim. We're going back to like
a פתיחה p'ticha and showing about, you know, it's sort of like
the והיא שעמדה לאבותינו ולנו V'hi She'omdah Lavoseinu V'lanu that, you know,
that we've, that there've always been these periods in history when it
looks like things were very bleak and in the end, you know,
sort of like what Mordechai says to Esther, רווח והצלה יעמדו ליהודים
ממקום אחר, revach v'hatzalah ya'amdu la'Yehudim mi'makom acher, in the end ultimately
God will come to save us. Okay, רבי לוי אמר מהכא, Rebbe
Levi amar me'hacha, ואם לא תורישו את יושבי הארץ, v'im lo torishu
es yoshvei ha'aretz, again sounding like we're going back and Rashi even
says by the way Rashi when says ושמואל אמר מהכא, u'Shmuel amar
me'hacha, if you look
at Rashi at the end of
the right hand column, פתחא פתחא לא מאסתים. p'ticha p'ticha lo ma'astim.
So we're going back, it's a little funny we're doubling back because
it sounded like again we were starting to finally look at the
פסוקים pesukim themselves, ויהי בימי אחשורוש, V'yehi Bi'ymei Achashveirosh, but we're
now again doubling back and talking about introductory פסוקים pesukim that would
open up the מדרשים midrashim on the מגילה. Megillah. So one was
this לא מאסתים ולא געלתים. lo maastim v'lo gealtim. רבי לוי Rebbe
Levi says ואם לא תורישו את יושבי הארץ, v'im lo torishu es
yoshvei ha'aretz, if you do not drive out the inhabitants of the
land, והיו לצנינים בצדיכם. v'hayu litzninim be'tzideichem. Now what does that have
to do with anything?
So Rashi says אף אלו נענשו על חמת שאול על עמלק, af
elu ne'enshu al chamat Shaul al Amalek, because ultimately this is all
a continuation of the עמלק Amalek story and that has to do
with the war of עמלק Amalek in the land of כנען, Kna'an,
in the land of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So ultimately this is
an end of that story and of what happened because they were,
he did not follow God's command. He would open up the פתיחה,
p'ticha, again we're back to פתיחות. p'tichos. We're not, we've abandoned the
the פסוקים pesukim of the מגילה, Megillah, I mean the actual, you
know, the פסוקים pesukim themselves, we're talking about how you would open
from a different פסוק pasuk and tie in the מגילה Megillah as
seen as part of this larger theme. And rhetorically too it suggests
that this was an oral דרשות drashos so people would be sitting
and wondering, hmm, how's he going to get? Right, that's a good
point as well meaning not only I was talking about how it
has the effect of making everything interconnected and particularly by the מגילה
Megillah making the מגילה Megillah part of a much larger sort of
you know anchoring it much more earlier into biblical history and into
this whole sort of like you know this this greater religious historical
arc, but what Dov says is also correct. When you open from
a bizarre פסוק pasuk your interest is engaged like, what does that
have to do with anything? And then you sort of see how
it gets tied in. This is in general like I said, if
you begin open up of מדרש רבה Midrash Rabbah at the beginning
of a פרשה, parsha, you're like oh, like בלק, Balak, I want
to see what the מדרש Medrash says on בלק, Balak, and you
open up at the beginning and he quotes some פסוק pasuk in
משלי Mishlei you've never heard of and it takes you right a
few paragraphs till you finally get to talking about בלק, Balak, you
know, but this is how they would do it. They would open
up from some other פסוק pasuk and then tie it in. That's
for example you speak of פסיקתא דרב כהנא Pesikta de Rav Kahana
which are all homilies on יום טוב Yom Tov and they all
have פתיחתא, p'tichta, they all start with something and go to something
and go to something. שקח, Shko'ach, yeah. Just a question about the
historical context, does it seem to you then that the enemies of
the Jews are presented as sort of an outside independent agent here
when it says because of the עמלק Amalek point or the point
of עמלק? Amalek? Yeah, interesting. You know, we're going to get a
little bit if we get to it today also the whole idea
of, you know, of which is also a positive but a non-Jew,
right, where God sort of says, you know, כורש, Koresh, you know,
my anointed one כורש, Koresh, you know, who will rebuild the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you know, who will sort of give the permission.
So there is a non-Jew, but he's still called God's anointed one.
The issue of, you know, of it all being part of God's
plan but then also
the issue of accountability, you know, is a tricky one, right? Because
if God, like, the question that all of the מפרשים meforshim ask
about about the,
the Egyptians, like if it's
part of the whole thing, ועבדום וענו אותם ארבע מאות שנה, va'avadum
v'inu osam arba meos shana, how could you punish the Egyptians if
they're just fulfilling, you know, God's plan? So, you know, there are
answers to that. I mean, the, the most sort of maybe the,
the most common one is just
because God says it's going to happen, and even if God says
the Egyptians are going to do it, doesn't mean that you, you
this particular Egyptian, you have to stand up and volunteer. So, you
know, but somehow it's a way of reconciling the fact of yes
there could be a divine plan and there could also be free
choice. You know, and somehow there's room for you as an individual
private citizen Egyptian. Again, I don't know how there's room for פרעה,
Pharaoh, but anyway, to make your personal free choice and that doesn't
have to, you know, necessarily, that isn't necessarily pre-dictated pre-ordained because of
God's divine plan. So I assume that the reason here that it's
avoiding sort of saying God sent them is that even though that's
not being denied, ultimately it's all part of God's plan, the more
you emphasize that, the more it gets them off the hook for
the bad deeds that they've done, you know, or it sort of
problematizes that issue. But I think you, you know, you, it's definitely
a very good point that it sort of makes it sound like
this is just like a random event in history, and then God
intervenes by sending the ישועה. yeshuah. But that clearly is, anyway, I
mean, isn't that like the whole biblical message? Right, the Egyptians subjugate
and God sends משה. Moshe. You know, this thing happens and then
God sends, right, בלק Balak sends for, talking about בלק Balak and
בלעם, Bilaam, you know, בלק Balak sends for בלעם, Bilaam, and then
God, you know, intervenes. Like so God's intervention is coming to save
the day, not sort of in terms of all of the like,
but then again in Egypt God hardens פרעה Pharaoh's heart. Right, and
in Egypt and that's why they all raise the question in Egypt,
well, how's God hardening his heart and how are you punishing the
Egyptians? Right, but in the מגילה Megillah you don't see that. Right,
but I think what David is saying is true, Egypt is like
the exception where it shows God being involved in, you know, in
the negative. And in the end that has to be dealt with,
but I think the more you make that point explicit, the more
you problematize so why are they deserving of punishment? So I think
that that's why it's often not, not made as explicit. To me,
I think it's very difficult to go the other way too, the
entire book of שופטים Shoftim is the Israelites sinned, right, and God
sends a scourge against them in the form of another nation and
then sends a savior and then that other nation is punished, and
the ראשונים rishonim it's, it's it comes up. It's a good point,
but I think in those stories you're not focused on the on
the punishment of the other nation. No, but I, no I understand,
but like when you talk about the Egyptians, the Persians, the Babylonians,
whatever, you want to get a feeling like they're going to get
paid back for all this bad stuff that they've done. Whereas it's
a good point, but I think in a way it, it fits
because in those stories in, you know, in שופטים, Shoftim, like we're
not focused on the punishment that these people get. We're focused on
the תשובה teshuva of the people and this was from God and
they got their punishment here. It's like these are big nations that
loom large and we want to be told that that it's not
just God is hitting us but that they did evil and they're
going to be punished. And you do get that other side I
think in ישעיה Yeshaya and עמוס Amos and הושע Hoshea and all.
In other words, the other nations then get paid back. Right, right,
but I think it's a good point but again I think that
that's not denied, but the more you make it explicit, then the
more it raises the question of why are they deserving of punishment.
That's fine. I'm sorry. Okay, yes. I think it's interesting how our
text picks up on on the word בימי אחשורוש. bimei Achashverosh. Right.
And then it talks about בימי היוונים. bimei Hayevanim. Oh, I see.
בימי בימי, bimei bimei, so it is still דורש darshening the first
פסוקים. psukim. And it's really talking about epochs of history, and and
I think that that makes it feel more that there is this
human history that's going on and God steps in or doesn't step
in at certain points in time to save the Jewish people. It
feels, it feels different than the other nations being mobilized to do
God's will. At least to me it feels that way. Okay, I
like that point, and the other point and again to bring that
out, what you're also point, point you're making is that as opposed
to just seeing this as a new פתיחה, psicha, in a way
it is getting to דורש darshen the פסוק pasuk of בימי. bimei.
What he's actually saying is that there are ימי, yemei, there are
periods in history where God intervenes. that dominate, like אחשורוש Achashverosh, *Achashverosh*
and פרסיים *Parsiyim*, right.
Yes. Okay, thank you. No, it's an excellent point. It's an excellent
point. So David is pointing out that the
point here is not just a פתיחה *peticha*, meaning I was looking
at the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of לא מאסתים ולא געלתים *lo maastim
velo gealtim*, which is like a פתיחה *peticha* from a separate verse.
But what David is saying is that what שמואל *Shmuel* might be
doing is focusing on the word ימי אחשורוש Achashverosh *Yemei Achashverosh*, there
have been various periods of history. There've been the period of אחשורוש
Achashveirosh *Achashverosh*, the period of the יוונים *Yevanim*, the ימי *yamei*... you
know, the ימי פרסיים *Yemei Parsiyim*. And always God, you know, in
these various periods, intervenes in these various periods of history. Thank you.
That's very nice. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this...
okay, where were we? Okay, we did רב לוי *Rav Levi*, we
did... okay. Now back to אחשורוש Achashveirosh. *Achashverosh*. רב חייא אמר amar,
מהכא *Rav Chiya amar meihacha*, והיה כאשר דמיתי לעשות להם אעשה לכם
*vehaya kaasher damiti laasot lahem eese lachem*. Again, that's a more of
a... you know, a more of a downer way of starting. So
the first... you know, again, this again does seem at this stage
to be the פתיחה *peticha*. So one is, this is all because
your fault because you didn't get rid of עמלק *Amalek*. And here
it's 'what I wanted to do to them I will do to
you', you know, if you do not get rid of these other
nations. So again, reemphasizing that you brought this upon yourself and it
almost led to complete destruction. Okay, so... so opening the פסוקים pesukim
*pesukim* from our responsibility in all of this having happened. Now we
get... now we actually do leave the פתיחות *petichot* fully behind and
we get to the... to the... to the opening פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*
of the מגילה Megilla. *Megillah*. So we did ויהי בימי *vayehi biyemei*.
Okay, now we're doing אחשורוש Achashverosh *Achashverosh*. אמר Amar, רב *Amar Rav*,
אחיו של ראש ובן גילו של ראש *achiv shel rosh uven gilo
shel rosh*. So אחשורוש Achashverosh *Achashverosh*, the brother of a head, of
a leader, and the בן גילו *ben gilo*, like of the same,
you know, character, of the same מזל *mazal* of the leader. What
does that mean? Who's the ראש *rosh*? אחיו של ראש *achiv shel
rosh*, אחיו של נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar. הרשע *achiv shel Nevuchadnezzar HaRasha* שנקרא ראש
*shenikra rosh*. The... like he's like a, you know, a colleague, he's...
he's just one of the same, cut from the same cloth as
נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar *Nevuchadnezzar*. שנאמר *Sheneemar*, as it says by נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar, *Nevuchadnezzar*,
אנת הוא רישא די דהבא *ant hu reisha di dehava*. בן... okay,
'you are the golden head'. Right, this is when there was this
dream and he didn't know what it meant, so it's, you know,
so... it was a statue with a gold head, and that's נבוכדנצר
Nevuchadnezzar? *Nevuchadnezzar*. Okay, בן גילו של ראש *ben gilo shel rosh*, anyway
he's the ראש *rosh*. Who... so what does it mean of the
same cloth cut from the same cloth as the head? הוא הרג
*Hu harag*, נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar *Nevuchadnezzar* killed, you know, the Jews. הוא אחשורוש
Achashverosh, ביקש להרוג *Hu Achashverosh bikesh laharog*, wanted to kill the Jews.
הוא החריב *Hu hechriv*, נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar. *Nevuchadnezzar* destroyed the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. הוא אחשורוש Achashverosh? ביקש להחריב *Hu Achashverosh bikesh lachriv*,
wanted to destroy. Now what does it mean wanted to destroy? So
this is going to be the question of when do we place
אחשורוש Achashverosh *Achashverosh* vis-à-vis the בית שני *Bayit Sheni*. So if you
look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, three lines from the top in the
left-hand column, להחריב *lachriv*, רש"י *Rashi* says, יסוד שיסד זרובבל בבית המקדש
בימי כורש Koresh? לפני אחשורוש Achashverosh? כמו שאמר בספר עזרא *yesod sheyasad
Zerubavel beBeit HaMikdash biyemei Koresh lifnei Achashverosh kemo sheamar beSefer Ezra*. So
this has אחשורוש Achashverosh *Achashverosh* after the original, the beginning of the
process of the rebuilding of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*.
The foundation has already been laid and included in אחשורוש *Achashverosh*'s edict
to wipe out the Jews presumably would be to destroy the foundation
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*. Okay, that's something that
we will get back to, but according to this at least has
אחשורוש *Achashverosh* once the process of the rebuilding has already been begun.
Is this word גילו *gilo* like גלגול *gilgul*, like he's a future
transmigration? Oh, I don't know. I hadn't... I don't know. I couldn't
answer that. I didn't think so. I mean, literally גיל *gil* is
an age, but I think it sort of means from like 'cut
from the same cloth' is usually what it means or it might
have more mystic, you know, metaphysical significance like born under the same
מזל *mazal* type of idea. Yes. That רש"י *Rashi* there would place
אחשורוש *Achashverosh* as being fairly early in the Persian period because כורש
Koresh *Koresh* allows them to start building... Right. Well we're gonna... we're
gonna get to that. We're gonna... so hold off. We're gonna get
to that whole... right. But רש"י *Rashi* says בימי כורש Koresh *biyemei
Koresh*, right? Okay, so we're gonna get to that. Okay, back in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. שנאמר *Sheneemar* ובמלכות אחשורוש בתחילת מלכותו *uvelmalchut
Achashverosh bitchilat malchuto*, as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* quoting the פסוק *pasuk*
in עזרא *Ezra*, כתבו שטנה על ישבי יהודה Yehudah, וירושלים *katvu sitnah
al yoshvei Yehuda veYerushalayim*. They wrote a, like sort of like a
negative, you know, edict against those who dwell in יהודה Yehuda. *Yehudah*
and ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. And רש"י *Rashi* says that שטנה *sitnah* is that
they were prohibited from continuing to build. So not even or not
necessarily according to this in the context of the story of פורים
Purim *Purim*, just סתם *stam* as a political act this is locating
it, even without the whole story of המן Haman *Haman* and פורים
*Purim*, based on the פסוק *pasuk* in עזרא *Ezra*, there's this אחשורוש
*Achashverosh*, assuming it's the same אחשורוש *Achashverosh*, that they stopped the rebuilding
of the Temple. ולשמואל אמר *UleShmuel amar*, שמואל *Shmuel* says, שהושחרו פניהם
של ישראל בימיו כשולי קדירה *shehushcharu pneihem shel Yisrael beyamav keshulei kedeira*.
אחשורוש *Achashverosh* is... so they are... they are... Because they felt that
they were about to be destroyed. So it's not about אחשורוש *Achashverosh*,
it's about the impact, you know, about what אחשורוש *Achashverosh* has. Someone
a little ties into the earlier שמואל *Shmuel*, that things are going
to happen to you, God is going to save you, so it's
sort of about us, you know, being subject to these impending, you
know, periods of, these oppression and disaster and then, you know, also
the whole question is, an issue that comes up for חז"ל *Chazal*
in this story is does this motivate the people to do תשובה
*teshuvah* and then God comes and saves and so on. So שמואל
*Shmuel* is certainly focusing on the impact that this has on the
people. Yes. אחשורוש *Achashverosh* is correlated historically with Xerxes? Is that correct?
Yeah, I mean I have Xerxes after, after Cyrus? Okay, you know
what, yeah, Cyrus is the first one that we... yeah. Cyrus. Okay.
Okay. Can we wait, let's wait until we turn the page, we
will get more to dating in a bit, if we get up
to it. Okay. רבי יוחנן אמר כל שזכרו אמר אח לראשו *Rabbi
Yochanan amar kol shezichro amar ach l'rosho*. Anybody who mentions אחשורוש *Achashverosh*
says woe to their head. They get a big headache. אח ראש
*ach rosh*, okay. אוי *oy* to their head. Okay. Meaning presumably not
just the Jews, but like that he was just a, you know,
he was a bad king or he was a foolish king or
whatever. Anyway, ורבי חנינא אמר שכל נעשו רשים בימיו *ve'Rabbi Chanina amar
shekol na'asu rashim b'yamav*. He made everybody poor. And again, not just
the Jews, שנאמר וישם המלך אחשורוש מס *shene'emar vayaseim hamelech Achashverosh mas*.
So you can't raise taxes even then it was political suicide. And
if you did, you got remembered forever for having made everybody, for
raised everybody's taxes. Okay. הוא אחשורוש *Hu Achashverosh*, okay. So either he
was very bad for the Jews, or he was bad for everyone.
הוא אחשורוש *Hu Achashverosh*. What does it mean הוא אחשורוש *Hu Achashverosh*?
הוא ברשעו מתחילתו ועד סופו *hu b'risho mitechilaso ve'ad sofo*. He was
unchanging, he was constant. He was wicked from the beginning to the
end. Now that we're saying that that's what the הוא *hu* means,
we're going to דרשן *darshan* other הואs *hu's* by in the תורה
*Torah*. הוא עשו אבי אדום *Hu Eisav avi Edom*, so פסוק *pasuk*
in בראשית *Bereishis*, so הוא ברשעו מתחילתו ועד סופו *hu b'risho mitechilaso
ve'ad sofo*. He was wicked from beginning to end. הוא דתן ואבירם
בני אליאב *Hu Dasan va'Aviram b'nei Eliav*, right, in פסוק *pasuk* in
במדבר *Bamidbar*, הן ברשען מתחילתן ועד סופן *hein b'rishon mitechilasom ve'ad sofom*,
and they were wicked from beginning to end. הוא המלך אחז *Hu
hamelech Achaz*, he is King אחז *Achaz*, הוא ברשעו מתחילתו ועד סופו
*hu b'risho mitechilaso ve'ad sofo*. He was always a wicked king. אברהם
הוא אברהם *Avraham hu Avraham*, פסוק *pasuk* you probably haven't heard, which
is in דברי הימים *Divrei Hayamim*, הוא בצדקו מתחילתו ועד סופו *hu
b'tzidko mitechilaso ve'ad sofo*. He was always righteous. הוא אהרן ומשה *Hu
Aharon u'Moshe*, he is אהרן ומשה *Aharon u'Moshe*, הן *hein* or they
הן *hein*, it's in the פסוק *pasuk* in שמות *Shmos*, בצדקתם מתחילתם
ועד סופם *b'tzidkasam mitechilasom ve'ad sofom*, they were always righteous. ודוד הוא
הקטן *ve'Dovid hu hakatan*, so he was the small one amongst the
sons of ישי *Yishai*, הוא בקטנותו מתחילתו ועד סופו *hu b'katnuso mitechilaso
ve'ad sofo*. Now what does that mean? That one needs to be
explained a little, he wasn't always small, he became a king. So
it means, כשם שבקטנותו הקטין עצמו למי שגדול ממנו בתורה *kesheim sheb'katnuso
hiktin atzmo l'mi shegadol mimenu b'Torah*, the same way when he was,
you know, just a youth and he wasn't king, he knew proper,
he knew how to be, you know, deferent and to make himself
small, you know, in the presence of one that was greater than
him in תורה *Torah*, כך במלכותו הקטין עצמו למי שגדול ממנו בחכמה
*kach b'malchuso hiktin atzmo l'mi shegadol mimenu b'chochmah*, so he showed deference
to those that were wiser than he, you know, maybe it's interesting,
sometimes it has דוד *Dovid* as like, you know, as a rabbi,
right, sitting and, you know, in the beginning of ברכות *Berachos*, פסקינן
שאלות *paskening shailos*, מפיבשת *Mephibosheth*, שבושת *sheBosheth*, you know, sort of bested
him in תורה *Torah*. So it could have said he knew how
to make himself small in front of others in תורה *Torah* when
he became a king. But in a way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is I think saying even a bigger point. It's one thing to
say, okay, I'm a king, I'm not a big תלמיד חכם *talmid
chacham*. I defer to somebody who's a bigger תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*
when it comes to a תורה *Torah* area. But חכמה *chochmah* is
like judgment, wisdom, knowledge, right, even there he was, which is maybe
you're king, you should know, even there he was willing to show
proper deference. Okay, המלך *hamoleich*, so that's הוא אחשורוש *Hu Achashverosh*. So
we've said that he's, he was always wicked and he was a
terrible king or he did ter-, you know, he was a colleague
of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar *Nevuchadnezzar*. הוא *hu* now. המלך מהודו ועד כוש *hamoleich
meiHodu ve'ad Kush*. So המלך *hamoleich*. Where were we? Okay. אמר רב
שמלך מעצמו *Amar Rav shemalach mei'atzmo*. So it's not that he was,
you know, the son of a king, but he was a self-appointed
king. He rose from the commoners. אמרי לה לשבח ואמרי לה לגנאי
*ami lei l'shvach ve'ami lei l'gnai*. Some say that this actually is
a positive thing about him and some say that it's a negative.
אמרי לה לשבח דלא הוה איניש דחשיב למלכא כוותיה *ami lei l'shvach
d'lo hava inish dechashiv l'malka k'vasai* that it's a good thing, look,
nobody else was fit to be king other than him, so he
was, he was taken from amongst the commoners, he was the most
fitting to be king. ואמרי לה לגנאי *ve'ami lei l'gnai*, some say
that it's a negative character characteristic of him, דלא הוה חזי למלכות
וממונא יתירא הוא דיהיב קמי *d'lo hava chazi l'malchus u'mamon yaseirah hu
d'yaiv kamei*, that he wasn't fit for kingship and money, extra money
is what he gave to them. he really wasn't fit to be
king, he just gave a lot of money, maybe evoking what חז"ל
*Chazal* sort of knew in terms of the whole issues around like
the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* about people could buy their way into
important positions. So maybe he was chosen not because of his qualities,
but he was just chosen because he bribed his way into it.
Right? You used to be able to also buy the papacy. Wasn't
that true? There were some Jewish popes? Oh, come on, that couldn't
happen in politics. Right, okay, or religion. I know Jewish popes but
there were definitely popes who bought the office as there were high
priests who bought... Well, I mentioned the high priests already. Okay, but
I act... anyway. Alright, okay, where were we? Okay, בהודו ועד כוש
*me'Hodu ve'ad Kush*. So he ruled over from Hodu, from India to
Ethiopia. רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*. חד אמר *Chad amar* הודו בסוף עולם
וכוש בסוף עולם *Hodu besof olam veKush besof olam*, they're at opposite
ends of the world. וחד אמר *vechad amar* הודו וכוש גבי הדדי
הוו קיימי *Hodu veKush gabei hadadi havu kaimei* that they were right
next to one another. So if they're opposite ends of the world,
we understand, but what's the point if they're right next to one
another? To say כשם שמלך על הודו וכוש *keshem shemalach al Hodu
veKush*, the same way he had he ruled over these two countries
that were right next to one another, כך מלך melech מסוף העולם
ועד סופו *kach malach misof ha'olam ve'ad sofo*, he had control over
the entire world. So he ruled over the entire civilized world. So
הודו ועד כוש Hodu ve-ad Kush, *Hodu ve'ad Kush* might not mean
from one end to the other, it might mean with that same
degree of control. Okay, it does not seem to be פשט pshat
*peshat* of the פסוק *pasuk*. I once had a rabbi that told
me they're both right, because if they're opposite ends of the world
then they're right next to each other, right, depends on which direction
you're going. Okay, anyway. There was a Kush or Kushan, well in
English it's Kushan Empire in center around what is now Afghanistan. Oh,
but that was a little later than the Persian empire. Interesting, but
it would have been around by the time they did it. Interesting,
okay, weird. And in fact the Hindu Kush mountain range in Afghanistan
and Pakistan gets its name from it. Okay, so they're actually both
right. Okay, very nice, different Kushes. And the Kush in Ethiopia. Right.
Yes. And Kush was applied to actually more Sudan than Ethiopia but
much long earlier than the Kush that's in Georgia. Right. Okay, but
היחלף *Hayachalef* the פסוק *pasuk* in where is it? In ירמיה Yirmiyah
*Yirmeyahu*, היחלף כושי עורו ונמר חברבורותיו *Hayachalef Kushi oro ve'namer chabarburosav*, right,
will a Kushite change his skin or a leopard his spots? Yeah.
Yeah. So presumably it does mean Ethiopia. Right. So anyway, but that
makes sense. Okay, right. Kush and the situation were well established. Okay,
so okay, so the פסוק *pasuk* going on. Okay. כיוצא בדבר אתה
אומר *Kayozei badavar atah omer*, in a similar way, there's a debate
about the following פסוק *pasuk*. כי הוא רודה בכל עבר הנהר מתפסח
ועד עזה mi-Tiphsah ve-ad Azzah. *Ki hu rodeh bechol ever hanahar mitafsach
ve'ad Azah*. This is by שלמה Shlomo, *Shlomo*. He had dominion over
the entire Trans-Jordan from Tafsach to Azah. So what does that mean?
רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*. חד אמר *Chad amar* תפסח בסוף עולם ועזה
בסוף עולם *Tafsach besof olam ve'Azah besof olam*. So here's Gaza right
in the news. So Tafsach is at one end and Gaza, עזה
*Azah* is at the other end, then he ruled over the entire
inhabited world. וחד אמר *Vechad amar* תפסח ועזה בהדי הדדי הוו קיימי
*Tafsach ve'Azah behadi hadadi havu kaimei*, they were right next to each
other, כשם שמלך על תפסח ועל עזה כך מלך melech. על כל
העולם כולו *keshem shemalach al Tafsach ve'al Azah kach malach al kol
ha'olam kulo*. The same way he had dominion over these two places
which are right next to each other, he had dominion over the
whole world. Okay, שבע ועשרים ומאה מדינה *sheva ve'esrim u'meah medinah*, 127.
אמר רב חסדא *Amar Rav Chisda*, בתחילה מלך melech, על שבע ולבסוף
מלך על עשרים ולבסוף מלך על מאה *betchilah malach al sheva ulevasof
malach al esrim ulevasof malach al meah*, which is a funny דרשה
drasha *drashah* because it's the way the תורה *Torah* normally just counts
numbers, right, it's like ויהיו ימי חיי שרה מאה שנה ועשרים שנה
ושבע שנים *va'yihyu yemei chayei Sarah meah shanah ve'esrim shanah ve'sheva shanim*,
right, 7, 10, and 20 years, 7, right. So anyway, so here,
right, so there's a דרשה *drashah* there, but that's the way, you
know, רש"י *Rashi*, the famous דרשה *drashah*, 70 like 20 for state
and 20 whatever for beauty. Anyway, but that's the way the תורה
*Torah* quotes numbers, which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will ask. So anyway
he says he started with seven, then he became king over twenty,
then he became king over a hundred. אלא מעתה *Ela me'ata*, says
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, if that's how you read it, ושני חיי
עמרם שבע ושלשים ומאת שנה *u'shenei chayei Amram sheva u'shloshim u'mas shanah*,
and the life of Amram was seven and thirty and a hundred
years, מאי דרשת ביה *mai darsht bei*, so what are you what
דרשה *drashah* are you going to give for that if you're going
to דרשן *darshan* the separation of the numbers? So שאני הכא דקרא
יתירה הוא *shani hacha dekra yeseirah hu*. No, here we can make
the דרשה *drashah* because it's superfluous. מכדי כתיב מהודו ועד כוש *michdi
kesiv me'Hodu ve'ad Kush*, it already tells us Hodu and Kush. ושבע
ועשרים ומאה מדינה למה לי *vesheva ve'esrim u'meah medinah lamah li*, why
does it tell me 127? I mean obviously it's the whole inhabited
world. So שמע מינה לדרשה *shema minah ledrashah*, it must be for
a דרשה *drashah*. I mean not, you know, it certainly makes it
a little bit more graphic when you list the number, but okay,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to make this דרשה *drashah*. Not even
clear what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to bring out of this
דרשה *drashah*. Like what do I care, you know, if he worked
his way up? If anything that reinforces, you know, that's always going
to be the question about אחשורוש *Achashverosh*, right, מלך טיפש *melech tipeish*
or מלך חכם *melech chacham*. Like do we make him foolish or
do we think that he was a powerful king? So again if
you make the story that he sort of he grew grew his
kingdom from 7 to 20 to 100, it makes him a powerful
king. So anyway other than that it's not clear what the focus
is on that. Okay, תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*. Now that we're speaking
about him ruling over the whole world, we're going to extrapolate, expand
upon that a little bit. move away from the פסוקים psukim for
a moment. From the פסוקים psukim. of the מגילה. Megillah, שלושה מלכו
בכיפה: Sheloshu malkhu bikippa: three ruled under the dome, meaning three had
dominion over the entire inhabited world. ואלו הן: ve-alu hain: these are
they: אחאב ואחשורוש ונבוכדנצר. Achav, ve-Achashverosh, u-Nevuchadnezzar. אחאב, Achav, אחשורוש, and נבוכדנצר.
Nevuchadnetzar So excellent. So תוספות Tosafot says, you look at the little
תוספות Tosafot stuck in here on the left, ואמאי לא חשיב אלכסנדרוס
מוקדון, ve-amai lo chashiv Alexandros Mukdon, right? How about Alexander the Great?
משום דלא הוו חשיבי אלא הנהו דכתיב בהו הדיוט. mishum de-lo havu
hashivi ella hanehu de-ketiv behu hedyot. אין ain פסוקים Psukim about Alexander
the Great. So he came unfortunately for him, he came after the
biblical period, so he did not get to be included in the
list. These are only people that are in the תנ"ך. Tanakh. Okay,
אחאב דכתיב חי ה' אלהיך אם יש גוי וממלכה אשר לא שלח
אדוני שם לבקשך. Achav de-ketiv chai Hashem elokecha im yesh goy u-mamlacha
asher lo shalach adoni sham le-vakeshcha. This is by, right, אליהו Eliyahu
that stopped the rain. And he says, you know, my master the
king sent to every single nation in order to seek you out.
והשביע את הגוי ואת הממלכה. ve-hishbiya et ha-goy ve-et ha-mamlacha. He made
them take an oath that they don't know where you are. ואי
לא דהוה מליך עלייהו, ve-i lo de-hava malich aleihu, if he did
not have any power over these other nations, היכי מצי משבע להו,
heichi matzi mashba lehu, how could he get them to take an
oath about whether they saw אליהו? Eliyahu? Obviously he was able to,
you know, exert his influence over these other nations. It doesn't literally
mean he ruled over them, but okay, that's the way the גמרא
Gemara is understanding it. נבוכדנצר דכתיב והיה הגוי והממלכה אשר לא יתנו
את צוארו או אשר לא, Nevuchadnezzar de-ketiv ve-haya ha-goy ve-ha-mamlacha asher lo
yitnu et tzavaro o asher lo, the side has the right version,
או אשר לא יעבדו אותו את נבוכדנצר מלך בבל ואת אשר לא
יתן את צוארו בעול מלך בבל. o asher lo ya'avdu oto et
Nevuchadnezzar melech Bavel ve-et asher lo yiten et tzavaro be-ol melech Bavel.
So anyway, every nation has to serve him and put their neck
through the yoke of the מלך בבל. melech Bavel. אחשורוש הא דאמרן.
Achashverosh ha de-amran. אחשורוש like we said, הודו ועד כוש, מסוף העולם
ועד סוף העולם. mi-sof ha-olam ve-ad sof ha-olam. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says ותו ליכא? ve-tu leka? So now there's a סימן siman
here, שסד"כ. shin samech dalet chaf. רש"י tells you what they stand
for: שלמה סנחריב דריוש כורש. Shlomo Sancheriv Daryavesh Koresh. So we're going
to ask, how about those other four kings? Didn't they rule over
the whole world as well? So let's take a look. Are there
no others? והא איכא שלמה? ve-ha ika Shlomo? How about שלמה, Shlomo
right? We just said, right, מתפסח ועד עזה. So the גמרא Gemara
says, of course when you read תנ"ך Tanakh you don't get a
sense that שלמה Shlomo was king over the whole world, but that
was the דרשה the גמרא Gemara had before. Marrying the daughters of
all these kings. I understand, exactly. So the גמרא Gmara says, no,
לא סליק מלכותיה. lo salik malchutei. His kingship did not like conclude
well because there's a famous story how he ended, that he actually
went a little crazy and he lost his kingship and he was
a commoner. So the גמרא Gmara, says, הניחא למאן דאמר מלך והדיוט.
hani-cha le-man de-amar melech ve-hedyot. That's good according to the one that
says he started as a מלך and he ended as a הדיוט,
hedyot, so he didn't end his life as a מלך. אלא למאן
דאמר מלך והדיוט ומלך, ela le-man de-amar melech ve-hedyot u-melech, that in
the end after he had that period of, you know, having been
a commoner, he once again became מלך, מאי איכא למימר, mai ika
le-meimar, what can you say? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, שלמה
מילתא אחריתי הוה ביה. Shlomo milta achrita hava bei. So שלמה wasn't
counted not because he wasn't ruler over the whole world, but because
he was even more than ruler over the whole world. He was
in a category all by himself, דמלך אעליונים ואתחתונים. de-malach a-elyonim ve-atachtonim.
He also had dominion not only on the lower realms but on
the supernal realms over the שדים shedim and all those other stories,
שנאמר וישב שלמה על כסא ה', she-ne'emar va-yeshev Shlomo al kisse Hashem,
the throne of God. So just like God, he had dominion not
only over the physical lower world but even over the metaphysical world
as well. So he's in a category by himself. Okay, so גמרא
says והא איכא סנחריב? ve-ha ika Sancheriv? How about סנחריב? Sancheriv? דכתיב
מי בכל אלהי הארצות האלה אשר הצילו את ארצם מידי? de-ketiv mi
be-chol elohei ha-aratzot ha-eleh asher hitzilu et artzam mi-yadi? Who from all
these other nations have saved their lands from me? So סנחריב Sancheriv
clearly had conquered the world. גמרא says, האיכא ירושלים דלא כבשה. ha-ika
Yerushalayim de-la kavsha. Yeah, but the end of the story is that
he doesn't conquer Judea and Jerusalem. והא איכא דריוש? ve-ha ika Daryavesh?
How about דריוש? Daryavesh? דכתיב דריוש מלכא כתב לכל עממיא אומייא ולשניא,
de-ketiv Daryavesh malka ketav le-chol amemaya umaya ve-lishanaya, דריוש Daryavesh the king
wrote to all of the nations, nations and tongues, די דיירין בכל
ארעא שלמכון ישגא, di dayarin be-chol ar'a shelomachon yisgei, that live in
all the lands, let your peace, you know, much peace unto you.
So anyway, if he's writing to all the nations, presumably because they're
all under his dominion. גמרא says, no, האיכא שבע דלא מליך עלייהו.
ha-ika sheva de-la malich aleihu. No, he only had 120, he didn't
have 127, דכתיב שפר קדם דריוש והקים על מלכותא לאחשדרפניא, de-ketiv shepar
kodam Daryavesh ve-hakim al malchuta le-achashdarpanaya, it was good in the presence
of דריוש Daryavesh and he put over his kingdom for the various
provinces, מאה ועשרין, me'ah ve-esrin, 120. Some say 127. So he didn't
get the entire entire civilized world. Okay, והא איכא כורש? ve-ha ika
Koresh? How about כורש? דכתיב כה אמר כורש מלך פרס, de-ketiv koh
amar Koresh melech Paras, so says כורש the king of the Persians,
כל ממלכות הארץ נתן לי ה', kol mamlechot ha-aretz natan li Hashem,
all the kingdoms of the land God has given me. גמרא says
no, ה... ha... He's just praising himself. You can't take his words
for it. The other stuff the פסוקים Psukim, were saying that he
actually was writing to the other nations, here he's just praising himself.
I mean it's true when you look at these like stelae that
they find, you know, from the ancient world about kings telling about
their domain, right? They always describe themselves as like kings of the
whole world, right? You know? So yeah, you can't, you can't trust
somebody's own rhetoric. All right, moving on. Back to the פסוקים. What?
Oh, מה זה? ma zeh? What? Right, like it's just, it's just
known that he was once of the greatest, the greatest king ever,
right. Okay, so בימים ההם כשבת המלך אחשורוש. bayamim hahem keshevet hamelech
Achashveirosh. Okay, in those days, when the King Achashveirosh sat on his,
on his royal throne, וכתיב בתריה בשנת שלוש למלכו uch'tiv batreia bishnat
shalosh lemalcho and in the year three he made a משתה לכל
שריו ועבדיו. mishteh lechol sarav va'avadav. So what is it? Was it
as soon as he became king or did he wait or year
three? So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so said Rava, מאי כשבת, mai
keshevet, what does it mean when he sat on his throne? So
it means לאחר שנתישבה דעתו, le'achar shenityashva da'ato, after he became settled.
Meaning he wanted to make this big feast when he started, but
כשבת keshevet he needed to first feel confident and wait three years
and then he made this big feast. Now why did he have
to wait three years? What was he feeling confident about? So now
we're going to get to the dating of it, okay? So אמר,
he said the following, בלשצר חשב וטעה. Belshatztar chashav veta'ah. Belshatztar did
the math, computed it, and made a mistake, because the whole idea
is that both in ירמיה Yirmiyah, and in דניאל Daniel it says
that the redemption from the first destruction will come after 70 years
of exile. So the גמרא understands that these kings that came after,
the Persian kings, בלשצר Belshatztar and then אחשורוש or whatever, these kings
knew these prophecies, they did the math and that they were, the
reason that they sort of had the confidence that they did to,
as we'll see, do what they did was because they figured, look,
the prophecy did not come true. Okay, and as with all prophecy,
it was intentionally ambiguous, so they got the math wrong. All right,
so let's take a look. So בלשצר חשב וטעה, Belshatztar chashav veta'ah,
he did the math and he made a mistake. אנא חשיבנא ולא
טעינא, ana chashivna velo ta'ina, I'll compute and I won't make a
mistake. מאי היא, mai hi, what's meant by this? דכתיב, dech'tiv, because
it says in ירמיה, כי לפי מלאות לבבל שבעים שנה אפקד אתכם.
ki lefi melot leVavel shiv'im shanah efkod etchem. When it's full for
בבל Bavel 70 years then I will remember you and bring you
back. וכתיב למלאות לחורבות ירושלים שבעים שנה, uch'tiv limlot lechorvot Yerushalayim shiv'im
shanah, and when it's fulfilled for the destruction of Jerusalem 70 years.
The two prophecies about 70 years, one measuring from the destruction of
Jerusalem, the other from בבל. Bavel. Not exactly clear what that means,
בבל, Bavel, and whether these are the same, the same numbers or
not, the same starting point. So let's take a look. This is
what בלשצר Belshatztar did. חשב ארבעין וחמש דנבוכדנצר. chashav arba'in vachamesh deNevuchadnezzar.
He figured look, בבל Bavel means when נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar, became the king
of בבל, Bavel, that's the beginning of the dominion of בבל. Bavel.
So when בלשצר Belshatztar there was king, it had been 45 years
from בבל, Bavel, from נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnetzar ועשרין ותלת דאויל מרודך, ve'asrin utlat
deEvil Merodach, 23 from the king that followed, Evil Merodach, that gets
you to 68, ותרתי דידיה vetartei didei and two years since בלשצר
Belshatztar had been king. השבעים, hashiv'im, that made 70 years and he
figured oh, they haven't been redeemed, the prophecy didn't come true. Now
I can do what I want, I don't have to be afraid
of God, the prophecy didn't come true. This is בלשצר, Belshatztar, not
אחשורוש. אפיק מאני דבי מקדשא, afik manei devei mikdasha, he took out
the vessels of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash ואישתמש בהו, ve'ishtamesh behu,
and he used them. Okay, and then we're going to see and
then he got smitten dead in the middle of the night. Okay,
so but that's the story of בלשצר. Belshatztar. Now just to give
you, to let you know where this is going, right, you know
when we read the מגילה, we read like וכלים מכלים שונים vecheilim
mikeilim shonim and in a different נגינה, neginah, right? וכלים מכלים שונים.
vecheilim mikeilim shonim. Because according to the מדרש, Midrash, those were the
כלים keilim of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash, Why were they different
vessels? Because they were using at the party the כלים keilim of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, which is a repeat of the sin
of בלשצר. Belshatztar. So he did the same thing בלשצר Belshatztar did
thinking, I'm not going to get trapped, I'm going to do the
math right this time. So now we're first showing how בלשצר Belshatztar
had done this. Okay, so let's take a look. So now we're
going to figure out how you got this, 45 and 23 and
2. Okay, ונבוכדנצר מנלן דארבעין וחמש שנין מלך, veNevuchadnezzar minalan de'arba'in vachamesh
shanin malach, how do you know he was 45 years king, נבוכדנצר?
Nevuchadnetzar? דאמר מר, de'amar mar, because we taught, גלו בשבע גלו בשמונה
גלו בשמונה עשרה גלו בתשע עשרה. galu besheva galu bishmoneh galu bishmoneh
esreh galu betisha esreh. So based on different verses in תנ"ך, Tanakh,
it says that, you know, that they were sent into exile, we'll
see which exile, there were multiple exiles, but in the process of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. being destroyed, you know, or נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar,
taking over. So one it says it happened in the seventh year
and one in the eighth year, and then it says in the
18th year and the 19th year. So let's see what this means.
גלו בשבע לכיבוש יהויקים, galu besheva lechibush Yehoyakim, גלות יהויכין. galut Yehoyachin.
So יהויכין, Yehoyachin, right, which was one of the kings, last kings
in יהודה, so he was brought into exile and that was in
the eighth year— The eighth year and seventh year and one in
the eighth year and then it says in the eighteenth year and
the nineteenth year. So let's see what this means. גלות בשבע לכיבוש
יהויקים. Galut b'sheva l'kivush Yehoyakim. So גלות יהויכין. Galut Yehoyachin. So יהויכין,
Yehoyachin, right, which was one of the kings, last kings in יהודה.
So he was brought into exile and that was in the seventh
year from the exile of יהויקים. Yehoyakim. So a little confusing, יהויקים,
Yehoyakim, יהויכין. Yehoyachin. Anyway, which occurred is the seventh year of נבוכדנצר.
Nevuchadnetzar So basically what you have here is, so here's his year
one, and year two of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar. you have גלות יהויקים, Galut
Yehoyakim, okay, and then in year eight of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnetzar. you have
גלות יהויכין, Galut Yehoyachin, okay, which is גלות בשמונה, Galut b'shmonah, but
it's seven from the first the beginning of the exile. So that's
when some פסוקים talk about the exile in the seventh year, there's
a contradiction in פסוקים, and some say this exile happened in the
eighth year, it depends whether we're counting from year one or from
year two because year two is when the exile began. Okay, so
that's seven and eight. Where were we? גלות בשמונה עשרה, Galut b'shmonah
esrei, okay, כי שמונה לנבוכדנצר. ki shmonah l'Nevuchadnetzar. גלות בשמונה עשרה לכיבוש
יהויקים, Galut b'shmonah esrei l'kivush Yehoyakim, גלות צדקיהו, Galut Tzidkiyahu, תשע עשרה
לנבוכדנצר. tishah esrei l'Nevuchadnetzar. And then here in year 19 is when
you have גלות צדקיהו, Galut Tzidkiyahu, right, which is the real end
of the whole period, and that is 19 from year one of
נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnetzar. but it's 18 from the beginning of the process. So
that's just reconciling the verses of the various stages. There was one
exile that occurred in year eight and one in year 19, but
if you have a different counting, it's seven and 18. And that
actually corresponds to the secular sources too. Oh yeah? Okay, great. All
right, so it says like this. Okay. Where were we? כדאמר מר,
k'd'amar mar, because we talked תנא ושנא כבש שנים זה, Tana v'shana
kavash shnim zeh, in the first year of his dominion of being
king, he conquered נינוה, Ninveh, שניה כיבש יהויקים. shniya kivash Yehoyakim. In
the second year he conquered יהויקים Yehoyakim and that's how come some
of these countings start a year later because it's going from the
beginning of the exile. וכתיב: V'chtiv: ויהי בשלשים ושבע שנה לגלות יהויכין
מלך יהודה בשנים עשר חדש בעשרים וחמשה לחדש נשא אויל מרדך מלך
בבל בשנת מלכותו את ראש יהויכין מלך יהודה. Vayhi b'shloshim v'sheva shanah
l'galut Yehoyachin melech Yehudah b'shneim asar chodesh b'esrim v'chamishah l'chodesh nasa Evil
Merodach melech Bavel b'shnat malchuto et rosh Yehoyachin melech Yehudah. In the
37th year from the גלות Galut of יהויכין, Yehoyachin, אויל מרדך Evil
Merodach the king of בבל, Bavel, he took over after נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar
Babylonian, את ראש יהויכין מלך יהודה. et rosh Yehoyachin melech Yehudah. So
he then finally begin recognized, sort of raised in status יהויכין, Yehoyachin,
who had been taken into captivity, right, which is a long time
ago. He'd been 37 years in the dungeon essentially. ויוציא אותו מבית
הכלא, Vayotze oto mibeit hakela, and he took him out of the
dungeon. So here we go. Year 37, okay, is when אויל מרדך
Evil Merodach basically takes יהויכין Yehoyachin out of prison. Okay. So it's
37 years from the time of his exile. יהויכין's Yehoyachin been in
prison for 37 years and אויל מרדך Evil Merodach the next king
of בבל Bavel recognized him. That's a Babylonian end. So that's 37
years from the time that יהויכין Yehoyachin was in exile, which means
how many years is it from the beginning of נבוכדנצר? 45, right?
Okay. גמרא says, and that actually is consistent with when אויל מרדך
Evil Merodach did reign based on secular sources too. Okay, so תניא,
Tanya, so you've got the eighth of נבוכדנצר, פלוס plus 37, and
then 37 years from the exile of יהויכין, Yehoyachin, הרי ארבעים וחמש.
harei arbaim v'chamish. It was 45 years from the time נבוכדנצר was
king. To נבוכדנצר. That's the 45 of נבוכדנצר. ועשרין ותלתא דאויל מרדך,
V'esrim v'tlata d'Evil Merodach, 23 years אויל מרדך Evil Merodach was מרדוך,
Marduk, right? That's what we get the name מרדוך, Marduk, right? Amel-Marduk.
Like מרדכי. Mordechai. Okay, but anyway, moving on, plus 23 years אויל
מרדך Evil Merodach was king. גמרא, that's a tradition. So that gets
you to 68. ותרתי דידיה V'tartei dideih and אויל מרדך Evil Merodach
was followed by בלשצר, Belshazzar, so בלשצר Belshazzar had been king for
two years. That was 70 years from נבוכדנצר. ותרתי דידיה, V'tartei dideih,
הא שבעים. ha shivim. 70. אמר השתא ודאי תו לא מיפרקי, Amar
hashta vadai tu lo mifarki, it's been 70 years, they haven't been
redeemed, now they're certainly not going to be redeemed. אפיק מאני דבי
מקדשא, Afik mani d'vei mikdasha, he took out the vessels of the
בית המקדש, this is בלשצר, Belshazzar, ואשתמש בהו v'ishtamesh behu and he
used them. והיינו דקאמר דניאל, V'hainu d'kamar Daniel, so that's why דניאל
Daniel says to him: ומארי שמיא התרוממת, T'amrei shmaya hitromamta, you have
elevated yourself over the King of Heaven, ולמאניא די ביתיה v'le-manaya d'veiteh
and the vessels of His house, היתיו קדמך hey-tayu kadamach you had
brought in front of you. וכתיב: V'chtiv: בה בליליא קטיל בלשצר מלכא
כשדאה, Beih b'leilya ktil Belshazzar malka Kasdaya, and that night בלשצר Belshazzar
was killed, the king of the כשדים. Kasdim. So there, that was
his end. Okay, so this whole story about what we're going to
tell about אחשורוש already happened to בלשצר. Belshazzar. He thought, although אחשורוש
doesn't get executed in the middle of the night, but anyway, the
ultimate downfall, and he repeated that mistake. וכתיב: V'chtiv: ודריוש מדיא קבל
מלכותא כבר שנין V'Daryavesh Madaya kibel malchuta k'var shnin and דריוש Daryavesh
the מדיא Madaya received the kingdom as a son of. So you
have בלשצר, Belshazzar, you have Mordechai and בלשצר, Belshazzar, okay? That and
that was seventy years according to one counting, that's the Babylonians, and
then you had the מדיים, Medians, right? Which is what's-his-name? דריוש. Daryavesh.
דריוש, Daryavesh, but what's the difference between מדי Madai and פרס? Paras?
דריוש Daryavesh was the Persian Empire. Yeah, okay, פרס Paras ומדי, u-Madai,
right, so Persian-Median, yeah, it's sort of this transition, right? Yeah, exactly,
I'm not enough of a historian to tell you exactly that. But
what does the Daniel itself, the פשט pshat, is he took the
כלים keilim and then died at night, or that's the חכמים? chachamim?
No, I think that's פשט, you have to look at the ספר,
sefer, yeah, okay. The גמרא says, okay, so where were we? כסדאי.
Kasda. כסדאי. Kasda. וכתיב דריוש מדאה קיבל מלכותא. V'chsiv Daryavesh Madaya kibel
malchusa. Okay, so this is the Babylonians, כסדיים, Kasdi'im, בבל Bavel כסדיים.
Kasdi'im. And this is מדי Madai ופרס u-Paras starting with דריוש. Daryavesh.
Okay, so there's some stuff later on does not- is not consistent
with what's the source. Okay. And now we'll just start that. אמר,
so Rava said, אי מוטעי, Iy mut'ei, בלשצר Belshazzar made a mistake,
אנא חשיבנא ולא טעינא. Ana chashivna v'lo te'ina. I'll do the computation
and won't make a mistake. מי כתיב למלכות בבל? Mi ksiv l'malchus
Bavel? It doesn't say seventy years from the beginning of the kingdom
of בבל. Bavel. לבבל כתיב. L'bavel ksiv. Seventy years from בבל. Bavel.
So what does בבל Bavel mean? מאי לבבל? Mai l'bavel? לגלות בבל.
L'galus Bavel. The exile of בבל. Bavel. Because remember the פסוק said
in Daniel, חרבות ירושלים, Charvos Yerushalayim, the destruction of the Jerusalem, which
did not start when נבוכדנצר became king. So it's seventy years from
the exile. So exile here he's going to assume the exile is
going to mean יהויכין. Yehoyachin. יהויכין. Yehoyachin. Of course you could say
the exile is צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu down here. Okay, but he's going to
say no, starts from the exile, which is here, which gives me
it's going to be eight more years until the seventy years are
up. Okay. כמה בצירן? Kama b'tziran? How many years was he- did
he fall short? תמניא, Tmanya, eight. חשיב אינהו וחילופיהו. Chashiv ayu chilufayu.
So then for those extra eight years that now it's going to
take for the seventy, חדא דבלשצר, Chada d'Belshazzar, one year of בלשצר
Belshazzar because it was his third year that this event happened. The
seventy בלשצר Belshazzar thought were up in his second year. So this
is בלשצר's Belshazzar third- had a third year. וחמש דדריוש וכורש. V'chamesh
d'Daryavesh v'Koresh. And now it assumes that the entire reign of דריוש
Daryavesh and כורש was five years. Okay, so that's five and one
is six. Okay. ותרתי דידיה, V'tarti didei, two years of אחשורוש, is
eight. השבעים, Ha-shivim, that was eight, seventy counting from יהויכין. Yehoyachin. השבעים,
Ha-shivim, כיון דחזא דמלו שבעים ולא איפרוק, Kivan d'chazi d'malo shivin v'lo
ifruk, seventy years came up and they weren't redeemed. אמר השתא ודאי
שוב לא מיפרקי, Amar hasta vadai sulo mifriki, now they will not
be redeemed. And he repeated this in- of בלשצר. Belshazzar. אפיק מאני
דבית המקדש, Afik mani d'Beis Hamikdash, he used the vessels of the
בית המקדש, that's the כלים מכלים שונים. keilim mi-keilim shonim. ואשתמש בהו
V'ishtamesh behu and used them. בא שטן, Ba Satan, came the Satan,
ורקיד בינייהו v'rikei beineihem and sort of danced amongst them, והרג את
ושתי, v'harag es Vashti, right? It's interesting, right? You know, here they
were in the party. What was the result of the party? The
result of the party was that they started acting a little crazy
and you know, it led to the- it led to ושתי Vashti
being killed. So ultimately that was his downfall when he died, but
ושתי Vashti died and that ultimately began you know, the you know,
allowed for אסתר Esther to get in and allowed for the פורים
story. Although it is funny, right? Because בלשצר Belshazzar gets really punished,
he gets killed. What happened by אחשורוש? אחשורוש doesn't suffer any punishment,
I mean המן's thing got reversed, but what of אחשורוש? The only
punishment is ושתי Vashti got killed. Okay. So it's obviously clearly of
different proportions. On the other hand, he wasn't the nation that conquered
that destroyed the בית המקדש. Okay, so anyway we will pick up
with this tomorrow and figure out how come the seventy years did
not- was not, you know why אחשורוש's math was incorrect as well.